In our previous video,
we have seen about LLM Benchmarking,
after that many people have asked me
one question
Ok Balaji, now I can read the
benchmarks and leaderboards,
but how can I choose a better model
for my use case?
That's a valid question,
right? So what can I do?
I can ask your question and I can
directly suggest which model to use
But because of that, you are not
learning anything. So I thought
let's create a framework on how to
choose best model
So by the end of this video,
you will be able to understand this
framework
And after learning this,
you don't have any doubt about which
model to use
So without any delay, let's get
started. First let's address this
question, which model is best?
If someone asks which LLM model is
best in this space, by default they
will say either ChatGPT,
Claude, Gemini, LLaMA
All of these are best models,
but do you think it is a right
answer? Think about it
So let's say, you came here and
asked which is the best vehicle?
What will you say? Do you have a
concrete answer?
No, right? Because let's say cycle
is the best in two -wheeler segment
Maybe they want to talk about
motorbikes or maybe they want to
talk about ambulances
Maybe they want to talk about
trucks, right? So every scenario has
their own best thing
Similarly, every model or LLM is
good at something
So there is not a single model that
is best at everything.
Do you agree?
So if someone asks this question,
which model is best?
First thing you need to question is,
what is the thing that you are
looking for?
Are you looking for a coding agent?
Are you looking for maybe research?
Are you looking for something else?
So that constraint is very important
Because depending on that
constraint, which model to use
changes a lot
If you look at our previous video
regarding benchmarks, you look at
MMLU, MMLU Pro and Software Bench
Testing
Why did they do these benchmarks?
Because every model is good at
something
Not all models are good at
everything
But if there are general specific
questions, all the models are good
GPT, Claude, Gemini,
LLaMA, any open source models like
DeepSeek
You can use all of those things
But if you want a specific agent
that is dedicated for coding,
maybe use Claude models
They are better
But if you want very specific good
at research, maybe use GPT 5
.5 Pro version
They are good at research
So similarly, whenever you are asked
a question, which model is best?
The next answer is a question that
you should ask
What are you referring to in terms
of which category?
Which category is best?
That is the first thing
Now let's talk about the second
thing
There are two different tiers of LLM
models
One is closed source models and the
other is open source models
So when you talk about closed source
models, these models are trained
But the weights are not open to
public
You cannot download these models
So what are such examples?
In GPD, there are 5.5 models,
5.4 models, 5.3 models,
4.0 models
There are different different models
And in each of them, you have
maximum reasoning, extra effort,
normal reasoning, medium reasoning
There are different different
segment models
But all of these are the closed
source models
Similarly, when you come to Claude,
they have Opus 4.8, Opus 4.7,
Sonnet 4.6, Opus 4.6
There are different different models
And all of these are closed source
You cannot download these models
Similarly, there are 3.5 Flash,
3.5 Pro, 3.2 Pro models
But one of the important things is
When you are using closed source
models
You need to communicate via APIs
And when you are communicating via
APIs
What you need to do?
You need to pay for using these
models
You need to pay all the money you
use
And you need to pay for input tokens
You need to pay for output tokens
You need to pay for cash tokens
Every single thing
But the advantage of this is
If you are going via the closed
source models via API
They tend to perform really good
And that means the latency is also
good
And the speed is also good
And then we will also talk about the
accuracy or intelligence
All these are usually good
Because you are paying for these
models
So this is first thing
And second thing
When you want to choose an LLMs
You have other option which is
called as open source LLMs
So open source LLMs means
You can download these models on
your machine
If you have a hardware
So let's say you have a GPU
Or you have some servers that are
running up
And you don't have to pay money
Because you have the hardware with
you
What you can do?
You can download these models
And you can execute these models on
your machine
And you can talk to them
There are different types of models
One of the famous models is LLaMA
These are from Facebook or Meta
And you have something from Mistral
Which is a lightweight very good
model
It seems to be built from France
And we have from China
We have DeepSeek and Qwen from
Alibaba
So these are the models which are
open source
You can download them directly
And use them in your machine
But you are using your machine's
hardware
That means your machine's hardware
Will get damaged quickly
So that is one thing
And these are right now not
as intelligent
As these models
Let's say 4.8 or Fable 5 or Mythos
Preview
Recently we have got 5.6 Sol and
Terra
And then the other model as well
So usually these models are not that
much good at intelligence
But many of the general tasks
All of these models can handle
without any issues
So either you can go via closed
source models
Where you use them via API
And you pay them using based on the
usage
Otherwise you can go via open source
models
And there are even more open source
models guys
Like Kimi and JP
There are so many open source models
You can use them if you are in the
learning phase
And one thing that I wanted to
explain
From my personal experience is
Usually companies prefer to go via
the closed source models
Because they are registered entities
And they have regulations that they
need to follow
Some of the open source models are
from DeepSeek or Qwen
It will be good if you download them
But if you don't download these
models
But if you use APIs for these open
source models
Then that is going to be a security
issue for many companies
Usually companies prefer to go via
closed source models
Even though they are little bit
costly
Because of security issues
Hopefully it is clear
And the next thing that I want to
talk about
When choosing an LLM model is
There are four pillars
The first pillar is cost
This is very important
You might have seen recently
Many companies like Microsoft or
Uber
There are so many companies
Who are creating or putting budget
on their AI spend
Because their employees are using
too much tokens
And because of that
AI spending has increased a lot
Monthly by monthly
And they thought let's cut it down
Why? Because the cost is too much
When you are using closed source
models
What did I say earlier?
Companies prefer to go via closed
source models
Even though they are paying high
cost
Because they are secure
And they are fast and they are
intelligent
So let's take an example
Let's say there is GPT 5.5
From GPT
And GPT 5.5
To use output tokens
If you want 1 million tokens
You have to charge 30 dollars
But this
If you go via DeepSeek
I think it can go for 2.5 dollars
For 1 million tokens
See the difference
Too much difference
If it is from open source models
So you need to think about
What is the task that you are doing
And do you think the task requires
That much intelligence
And if you go via Fable 5
Do you know the cost of Fable 5?
This is 50 dollars for 1 million
output tokens
Meaning
For 1 million output tokens
You are using 5000
And an engineer
In a month
How many million tokens will he use?
And that is why the bill is going to
Skyrocket
And these companies are putting a
budget on this bill
So you need to always think about
The cost
That is very important
And the second thing is
Quality
This is also very important
Let's say you have a research task
What is this research task?
You need to do a lot of analysis
On DNA
DNA is a very complex task
So here
You need to have a higher
intelligence
Yes
And with less intelligence
These tasks won't work
Even if you are using open source
models
So in such cases
I would tend to go via
Maybe GPT 5.5
Or Claude
Opus 4.8
Or Fable 5
It could be anything
Because they are very intelligent
And they are very very good at
research tasks
But
One of the backdrops when using
The intelligent models are
They are very big in size
And to use such big models
To start
When you talk about the speed or the
latency
It is going to be very high
Because
There is a big model
To load the whole model
And answer your question
It does a lot of thinking
And the speed will be very slow
So now you need to decide
Whether you want a speed model
Or an intelligent model
Because currently in the market
Either you can get a very high speed
Model with low intelligence
Or very high intelligence model
With low speed
You cannot have the balance between
these two
Right now
But you can try to tweak them
Based on your prompt
But there is a lot of engineering
that goes behind it
But let's not worry about that right
now
So some models
Let's say GPT 4.0 mini
It is not that much intelligent
But it is very fast
GPT 4.0 mini
So the question you need to ask now
Is
Whether
If my AI application needs
Fast answers or intelligent answers
So based on that
You can decide which model to use
And then the next thing
Is the context
So we already made a video
On YouTube called Context
Engineering
And if you haven't watched that
video
Please go ahead and watch it
So if you think about the models
like Gemini
So Gemini usually has
1 million to 2 million context
That means
You can put a lot of
Information into these LLMs
And you can chat on top of it
This is very important
Because you are building a multi
-stage
Agent
And there are so many things going
on
And for the agent to not lose
All of this context
If you use a model
Which is having higher context
window
It is going to be very helpful
So at that time
I would go via Gemini
There are some models in GPT
Which has like 300k context or 1
million context
So it depends on
Use case to use case
I think LLaMA is also approximately
250 to 300k context
If I remember correctly
So you need to decide
Whether how much of the
Context that your application needs
How many tools are you using
How many MCPs are you using
Whether do you have a rag or not
So if you need higher context
Models
Then I would go via Gemini
And another advantage in Gemini is
You have multi -modal capabilities
as well
So Gemini can create images
Can understand images
Can create videos
Every single thing
But GPT or Claude
They are not that much good at multi
-modal capabilities
They are very good at text
So you need to decide
What is our use case
In our use case
Whether do I need to have a multi
-modal machine
Or not a multi -modal machine
After that
I need to have an output latency
What kind of intelligence that I
would need
Taking all these factors
What is the budget that I can spend
Then you need to decide
Which models should I use
Open source models or closed source
models
Then that is how you will answer
Which model is best
Because
Choosing the model depends on
What is the use case that you are
trying to solve
Nobody will say this
And if you look at YouTube videos
They will say
GPT 5.6 came
Let's use every task for GPT 5.6
Why?
There is no need of using GPT 5.6
For every simple task
Now based on all of this
understanding
I am going to give you a quiz
So after every question
I will wait 30 seconds
In those 30 seconds
You think about it and answer in the
comment section
So first thing is
I have a question or a task like
this
Classify or
Extract intent from a million
Customer tickets per day
So everyday I get million
Tickets from the customer
In such tickets
I need to extract some information
Or I need to put an intent
classification
Is it positive ticket or negative
ticket
So which model
Will you use
for such tasks
So let me answer this
What is happening here
You have a million customer tickets
You have a high volume
So when you say high volume
You are going to burn a lot of
tokens
The first thing
So lot of tokens
And then second thing is
What is the task?
Extracting the intent or
classification
It is a very basic task
And even
The normal machine learning
Model can also do this
So in such cases
If you use a frontier model like GPT
5.5
Or 5.6
You are going to burn a lot of money
So in such situations
What I can do
I can pick any lightweight open
source model
Because
This is a very small task
And this doesn't require that much
intelligence
And then I can hit this
LLM
Multiple times for all of these
million
Customers
No matter how much I use
I am just only paying for the
hardware
But not for the API cost
So for such things
I will use a lightweight open source
Model
I can use that
First question and second question
Answer questions
Over 300 page contract
Or a large code base
So what do you do
in such situations
So the answer is
Let's say if I go via cheap model
And when I go to a cheap model
Usually
Intelligence is less
And
Context window is also less
And if I need
To put this much information
In my LLM
I need the models which are having
Higher context window
Where is the higher context window
Gemini
Gemini models
The context window is higher
And then after that
I need to
Talk to a large code base
If we are talking about code base
That means the output capability
Or intelligence should also be very
good
So intelligence should also be more
So what I do in such situations
I will go
Via the models
Via API or closed source models
Maybe hopefully Gemini
Because I have a larger context
Window and they are good at coding
capabilities
As well and there is third question
A coding agent
That plans edits and
Files and loops over 20 times
What do you do in such situations
So what is happening here
Here an agent
Goes multiple times
And it needs to plan a lot
So I need intelligence
And also the speed
These two need to be more
Maybe I will go
Via OpenAI or GPT
Because they are intelligent
And they are speed enough good
enough
And I will go via API
Otherwise in this specific use
Case I think
I can even use a model
Like DeepSeek
Because DeepSeek model is also
A good intelligent model
And even that is better at coding as
well
So if I want to cut on the budget
side
I will go via DeepSeek
No, if I want to go
Via premium side
I would go via OpenAI or GPT
5.5 or 5.4
It depends on the type of task
That I am looking at
Let's think about the framework that
I decided here
So let's say you want to pick a
model
The first question that you need
To ask is
The data sent to that model
Can it leave the servers or not
If it doesn't need
To leave the servers
Then what should you do
You have to pick the model
From the API
Because you can send the data to the
API
If you think your data
Privacy is very important
And you cannot send the data
To anywhere
Then go via open source models
These are called open source models
Like LLaMA, Mistral, Qwen,
DeepSeek
And if you are going
Via API
Then there are 4 things
That you need to think about
Cost, Quality
Speed and Context
So let's say
You want a high volume
Or easy task
Then I will go via smaller models
Like LLaMA, Mistral
DeepSeek
Because even though they are
Open source models
They also provide via API as well
Quality is very important
Intelligence is very important
Then I will go via GPT
Or Claude or Opus or DeepSeek
Pro version
Speed is very important
Then I can go via Groq
What Groq does is
They designed their own
Chips
And you can talk to them at a rapid
speed
The speed is the only selling point
for Groq
And you can use this
And there is a model called Kimi 2.7
Even this is also very fast
And then if you want to have
Longer context models
Go via Gemini or Claude or DeepSeek
You can use all of these things
And then after this
This is what step 2 is
Take the cheapest model
And good enough for the other 3
So you need to find a balance
Between what is the cost
And what is the speed
And what is the important
intelligence that it has
And what is the context window
By balancing all these things
You pick a model
And then once you pick this model
You decide to use wherever you want
This is the framework
That will never expire down the line
For the next 2 years as well
That's it
When you ask a question
Tell me which model to use
Instead of me suggesting which model
to use
I want to give you the data or the
knowledge
On how to choose the best model
And if you think there is someone
Who needs to listen to this video
Please share it with them
And if you want more updates please
subscribe and like as well
Thank you so much
I will meet in the next one